## YILUN XU

Bellevue, WA • +1 (919) 961-7998 • xuxx0597@umn.edu

#### **SUMMARY**

Relentlessly curious professional with 9 years of analytical and managerial experience in transportation. Success in pursuing, managing, and delivering sustainable transportation projects that result in carbon emission reduction. Unique combination of engineering ethics, business acumen, and diverse perspectives with proven track records of project delivery. Recognized top performer and leader with bias for action, change, and impact.

## PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

DKS ASSOCIATES, Seattle, WA

## **Transportation Engineer**

December 2019 – Present

- Delivered City of Bellevue Green Fleet Strategy that removes 500 metric tons of carbon annually by managing project team, coordinating stakeholders, streamlining fleet utilization data, assessing infrastructure upgrade requirements and developing most practical charging scenario.
- Managed fleet and facility data collection process, involving vehicle duty cycle, utilization, domicile
  location data, and engaging cross-functional stakeholders, for zero-emission transformation of City of
  Tacoma's 900 heavy, medium, and light-duty vehicle fleet across five outdated facilities.
- Integrated operational and maintenance cost factors, including energy utility rate structure, into decision-making for most efficient charging scenario for King County Metro's 400 future electric vehicle fleet.
- Introduced carbon credit as a source of revenue to financially justify electric vehicle charger deployment on University of California, Davis campus.
- Received repeated recognitions from client, partners, and team members for exceptional performance in managing analyst team workflow and navigating jurisdictions' ambiguous approval processes for region's first complex center-running Bus Rapid Transit system.

# ALLIANT ENGINEERING, INC., Minneapolis, MN

### **Professional Traffic Engineer**

January 2017 – November 2019

- Leveraged Geographic Information System (GIS) techniques to graphically communicate complicated traffic control plans for Super Bowl LII resulting in timely completion of event traffic management planning in less than 4 months.
- Supported Twin Cities' sustainable transportation initiatives by completing D Line Bus Rapid Transit (BRT) corridor advanced traffic operation modeling, Red Line BRT Transit Signal Priority (TSP) analysis, Route 5 TSP implementation, and Oak St protected bike lane and pedestrian crossing study.

### Traffic Engineer I

August 2016 – December 2016

• Prevented unnecessary rework and saved up to 100 consulting hours and a month of project timeline by challenging existing processes and automating repetitive volume balancing tasks during advanced traffic operation modeling of \$350 million Twin Ports freeway interchange reconstruction in Duluth, MN.

# UNIVERSITY OF MINNESOTA, Minneapolis, MN

## **Transportation Engineer**

May 2013 - July 2016

- Awarded "University Services Star Performer" due to upgrading campus transit system with no increase in cost through managing origin/destination survey, influencing for data-driven decision-making mindset, leading planning committee, and project implementation.
- Led real-world roundabout experiment and analysis that shook stereotypes and doubled University community's approval rate of this efficient, unconventional, and innovative traffic control.

#### **EDUCATION**

UNIVERSITY OF WASHINGTON, Seattle, WA Web Development Coding Certificate (part-time)

December 2022 (Expected)

UNIVERSITY OF MINNESOTA, Minneapolis, MN

Carlson School of Management (part-time)

**Master of Business Administration** 

December 2018

NC STATE UNIVERSITY, Raleigh, NC

Master of Science, Civil Engineering (Transportation) and Statistics

May 2013

TONGJI UNIVERSITY, Shanghai, China

Bachelor of Engineering, Traffic Engineering

July 2011

## GLOBAL CITIZENSHIP AND LEADERSHIP

- DKS Diversity, Equity, and Inclusion (DEI) Committee, Chair July 2020 February 2022
  - Led committee to focus on activities aligned with defined mission and goals, emphasizing relevancy to business practices and developing champions.
- Global Business Practicums in Europe and Asia, Team Lead

March 2016 – June 2018

- O Strengthened client commitment by leading multinational MBA team to draw relevant best practices, lessons learned, business cases from successful innovation centers across US and China.
- Effectively supported partner teams' critical decision-making by proactively leading primary and secondary research under time pressure and competitiveness challenge.
- o Served as ally between conflicting team members to offer cultural insights, alternative perspectives, emotional supports, and actionable feedback.
- o Translated quantitative analysis on retail partners into meaningful insights and business case by leveraging analytical and communication skills, in development of European market entry strategy.
- International Department of Tongji University Student Union, Division Chief March 2008 April 2009

### TECHNICAL SKILLS

Data management tools – ArcGIS, Tableau, SQL, Excel Macro Web development techniques – HTML, CSS, JavaScript, API

### LICENSE AND AFFILIATIONS

Professional Engineer (PE) – Minnesota and Washington Institute of Transportation Engineers (ITE) – Western and Washington Districts (Member) Transportation Research Board (TRB) – Managed Lane Committee (Member)

### SELECT PUBLICATIONS

- Xu, Y. (2021). Using Location-based Services Data to Complement Multimodal Origin and Destination Survey A Case Study at the University of Minnesota Twin Cities Campus. *Presented at 2021 National Travel Monitoring Exposition and Conference*.
- **Xu, Y**., Fimpel, T. (2015). Visualization and Analysis of Trip Origin and Destination Data in GIS. *Presented at 9<sup>th</sup> National GIS in Transit Conference, Washington, DC*.
- Xu, Y. (2016). Relating Automatic Bicycle Traffic Volume Counts with Detection of Cyclists Enrolled in Bicycling Reward Program. *Presented at 2016 National Travel Monitoring Exposition and Conference, Miami, FL.*